3 Leadership ↑

No. 21 – Build Great Teams

At the core of most of the important work done in this world you will find a small, multi-skilled team with effective leadership focused on delivering a product of value to a customer.

Note that teams such as these are found in contexts as different as Jazz bands, Rock groups, filmmaking, agile software development and Lean Manufacturing, to name just a few obvious examples.

It’s now commonplace in business to take the work of teams for granted, but passive acceptance doesn’t always translate into active support.

Let me break my opening assertion down, and explain the significance of each of its components.

“A Small Team”

I mean something in the range of 3 - 15 members. Such a team, if organized well, has the following advantages.

Diversity of knowledge, abilities and perspectives.
Joint decision-making following joint discussion and consideration of alternatives.
Bonding and cohesion of team members, including reinforcement of shared team norms.
Social motivations for completing important work.
Direct communication between team members.

What’s magic about the size? Less than three, and you have a duet rather than a group: it’s more about the individuals and their relationship, and less about a team identity. More than fifteen, and it’s hard to maintain direct communication between team members. (And fifteen, by the way is an upper limit: for some sorts of teams, that may be too large a number.)

And note that the ideas of Decomposition, Cohesion and Loose Coupling should be employed in order to break down larger groups into these sorts of teams, and to break down larger problems into ones small enough to be assigned to these sorts of teams.

“Multi-Skilled”

For the sort of team I’m talking about, it’s important for the team to be relatively self-sufficient, which means that all or most of the skills important to the team need to be available within the team. This is different from the oboe section within an orchestra, or a steno pool, or any sort of pool of resources sharing similar skills. A multi-skilled team is empowered to act as a collective. A group of people with similar skills will not achieve the sorts of benefits I’ve listed above for a small team.

Note that a multi-skilled team is also often referred to as a cross-functional team.

“With Effective Leadership”

A team can be self-organizing, but it cannot generally be self-governing. Some leadership can be internal to the team, and some of it can come from outside the team, but effective leadership is generally required in order for a team to be consistently productive. The product development team needs its Steve Jobs. The jazz band needs its Miles Davis.

Ineffective leadership comes in several common forms. It can be too passive. It can be too self-absorbed, ignoring signals from the team itself, from its customers or from its partners. It can be too diffuse, consisting of too many leaders, from different functions and/or levels, who are not in alignment with each other.

Certainly one of the important functions of leadership is to make difficult decisions concerning the team’s direction. Sometime this involves saying “no” to some options that the team might otherwise pursue, if left to its own devices.

“Focused on Delivering a Product of Value to a Customer”

There are four important but closely related elements that I’m grouping together here:

Focus: the entire team must be focused on a goal.
Product: A concrete product forces hard decisions to be made, and forces the team to actually produce a tangible result.
Delivery: The team must deliver something in a limited timeframe, again enforcing a degree of discipline.
Customer: The product must be something of value to a real customer. Without the ability to visualize such a recipient, it is hard for the team to make the sort of often difficult trade-off decisions involved in any important work.

Note that a cross-functional team focused on delivery of a single product is sometimes referred to as an Integrated Product Team (IPT).

Important Team Characteristics

Let me give further emphasis to a couple of important team characteristics.

First is the cultivation of and adherence to team norms.

Software development is by its nature a particularly solitary activity. Much of the work involves one programmer, one keyboard and one computer. And the quality and quantity of the work being done in this way is often hard to observe directly.

This is one reason why Watts Humphrey commented:

Trying to change the behavior of software engineers is like herding cats. They are very independent people; they all have their own ideas, and they won’t tell you what they think, particularly if they disagree with you. They just do what they want to do.

– Watts Humphrey, Winning with Software: An Executive Strategy, 2002

And so it is often difficult for even the best-intentioned managers and coaches to influence the working habits of individual developers.

However, when a small team is working together to achieve a common goal, and when they are committed to delivering working software within a short period of time, and when they are allowed to self-organize, and when the idea of joint ownership of the software code is promoted, and when they agree on a definition of what it means to say they are “done” with a piece of software, then it turns out that the team itself is much more effective at enforcing common norms than is any outside agency.

When considering team implementation, it would also be wise to consider the Core Design Principles for Teams, as defined by Nobel Prize Winner Elinor Ostrom and evolutionary biologist David Sloan Wilson.

Another important team characteristic deserving of further emphasis is that of diversity. Research has demonstrated that teams with diverse perspectives and backgrounds tend to produce better results, even if the discussions within such a team tend to be a bit messier and less straightforward.

In one of our studies, we compared homogeneous and diverse groups trying to solve a murder mystery. The diverse groups reported that they didn’t work together very effectively, and they were less confident about their decisions than the homogeneous groups, yet they consistently outperformed those homogeneous groups.

– Katherine Phillips, “Diversity Helps Your Business – But Not The Way You Think”, 2009

What Can Be Debated

I’ve tried to summarize above many of the key learnings about effective teams that I’ve gleaned over several decades, based on my experience working as a team member and team leader, and also based on my observations and broad study of the topic in multiple contexts.

But, of course, in this brief overview I’ve just scratched the surface of the subject. Whole books have been written on the topic of teams. There is lots of room for discussion and debate on the various elements of teams and team building.

What Cannot Be Debated

At this late date, it’s probably not useful to waste time debating whether teams like these are important.

Some would say that there is “magic” in such teams, but I think it’s probably fairer to say that there’s not much of lasting value produced without such teams.

Wherever we look today, especially when we dig beneath the surface of any of our modern success stories, we find abundant evidence of the operation of teams that fit the description I’ve provided above.

Heck, I’ve so far avoided any mention of sports, but I think much of our obsession with this endeavor can be traced back to the importance of teams in our society. Every game day we see this fundamental reality played out on the field in front of us – with all of the corporate and societal trappings stripped away – laying bare the workings of two teams, with their members, their diverse skills, their leaders, their activities, their collaboration and, ultimately, their results, all there for us to observe and discuss.

Implications for Your Organization

Much of what I’ve said above is probably fairly non-controversial.

And yet…

What are the implications for the larger organization?

It is probably not too much of a leap to say that successful organizations will be those who do the most to foster, sustain and nurture such teams.

Yet how many organizations embrace this truth as one of their core operating principles?

Instead leaders of large organizations often seem to lose grasp of what’s going on within their teams, and as a result lose track of the effects their decisions may have on the operation of these teams. After all, if leaders observe the business norms of interacting only with those immediately above, below or adjacent to them in the organization, with only occasional ceremonial contact with any working teams, it is all too easy for them to insulate themselves from first-hand knowledge of what’s happening at this level of their organizations.

I think this is one reason why the the videos on Spotify Engineering Culture have been so popular. There are a lot of great ideas here, but many team members simply seem to like the fact that a major company thinks their teams are so important that they will release content entirely focused on the way their teams function.

Let me return to my original assertion:

At the core of most of the important work done in this world you will find a small, multi-skilled team with effective leadership focused on delivering a product of value to a customer.

If this is true, then you need to ask yourself: what is your organization doing today to create, nurture and sustain these sorts of teams?

For more on this topic, see the Pagan Tuna post “The Power of Diverse Teams.”

Words from Others on this Topic

Prior to Steve Jobs’ return to Apple, there was a decent centralized usability team equipped with those fancy rooms with one-way mirrors and video cameras. I’m certain these folks did significant work, but when Jobs returned, he shut it down and he cast the design teams to the wind. Each product team inherited part of the former usability team.

Now, I arrived after this reorganization occurred, so I don’t know the actual reasoning, but I do know I never saw those usability labs used once and I would argue that in the past decade Apple has created some of the most usable products out there. My opinion is that the choice to spread the usability design function across the engineering team was intended to send a clear message: engineer and designer need to party more… together.

I can’t imagine building a team responsible for consumer products where engineers and designers weren’t constantly meddling in each other’s business. Yes, they often argue from completely opposite sides of the brain. Yes, it is often a battle of art and science, but engineering and design want exactly the same thing. They want the intense satisfaction of knowing they successfully built something that matters.

– Michael Lopp, Managing Humans: Biting and Humorous Tales of a Software Engineering Manager, 2007

No man is more important than The Team. No coach is more important than The Team. The Team, The Team, The Team, and if we think that way, all of us, everything that you do, you take into consideration what effect does it have on my Team? We’re gonna believe in each other, we’re not gonna criticize each other, we’re not gonna talk about each other, we’re gonna encourage each other.

– Bo Schembechler, “The Team”, 1983

Next: Govern Wisely

3 Leadership ↑

No. 24 – Consider What Might Go Wrong

An important role of leadership is to consider all the things that might go wrong, and then to ensure they don’t, or to respond appropriately when they do. Within a development team, it is frequently the project manager who plays this role, with strong support from line management.

Ideally this role is played by someone who can be firm with the team without being grim or demeaning or overzealous. Most of the team will be spending most of their time following the project’s “happy path,” and that’s as it should be. But someone needs to be the responsible parent, looking out for icebergs ahead that could ruin everyone’s journey, and then executing appropriate plans to avoid those sorts of threats. When this is done right, it often appears to be meaningless busy work, but when it is done poorly, or not done at all, it can result in serious impediments to the successful completion of the project, or even outright project failure.

Note that the project management discipline of risk management is part of this responsibility, as is the management of a project’s quality program.

Risk management should not be treated as a spectator sport – too often it consists of nothing more than documenting and reviewing risks, without actually doing anything to avoid their consequences. And risk reviews with leadership should be more than elaborate ceremonies conducted only to convince everyone involved that all risks are within acceptable bounds and so require no real action. In order to effectively manage risks, you must plan real work to reduce the likelihood of a risk occurring, and/or plan an alternative solution should your worst case scenario come to pass.

Words from Others on this Topic

The outcome of successful planning always looks like luck to saps.

– Dashiell Hammett, The Dain Curse, 1929

In retrospect, when we as project managers did not explicitly manage our risks, we were being childlike. Our whole industry has been childlike in this respect. Our infatuation with positive thinking and a can-do attitude has fixated us on the best outcomes as we ignored the various realities that could make such outcomes impossible. Considering only the rosy scenario and building it into the project plan is real kid stuff.

– Tom DeMarco and Timothy Lister, Waltzing with Bears: Managing Risk on Software Projects, 2003

Next: People

2 Fundamental ↑

No. 5 – Create Value for Customers

Developers must be focused, not just on writing code, but on creating value for their customers.

Let me qualify what I mean by “customer” and “value.”

A customer is a person or organization willing to pay for an item.

The term “customer” includes users of an item, but is not necessarily limited to those who directly use an item, especially in an enterprise setting where someone else is taking financial responsibility for the development of an item.

Value is a subjective assessment of an item’s worth.

Value often has both utilitarian and aesthetic dimensions: that is, an item is generally assessed based on how much it does for someone as well as how easy and pleasing it is to use.

Value is relative: it is assessed based on how much more one item delivers compared to other similar items already available.

Value is often time-sensitive: an item may be valuable today, but not be nearly so valuable a year from now (based on changing market conditions, etc.).

Value only exists when an item is complete and available for use: partially-developed items not yet ready to be used have no value at all.

Although value can be discussed without reference to monetary measures, a discussion of how much a customer might be willing to pay for an item is ultimately necessary to give a discussion of value some grounding in reality.

As mentioned above, value means more than just the ability to reliably perform a given task: the software must also be easy and reasonably pleasant to use. This is more than just a matter of “gussying up” the user interface – the developer must understand how his users think, and communicate to them using words and graphics that are consistent and effective. Most fundamentally, the software must be built around a mental model with which the user is already familiar, or that seems intuitive once learned.

Although developers need to form ideas about what will be useful to a set of users before developing software, those ideas can never be fully validated without actually developing the software and seeing what real users actually do with it. This is one reason why usability testing is so important.

Words from Others on this Topic

For years, app dev pros have been told to keep their heads down – that all you need to do is follow the project plan and write your code. Wrong. Lift your head up, find your passion, understand the business and then use your technical creativity to make beautiful applications that users find useful, usable, and desirable.

– Mike Gualtieri, Excuses, excuses: The Business Doesn’t Know What It Wants, 2009

In short, the software designer must learn to think like a communicator and to practice an artistic craft as well as an engineering one.

– Paul Heckel, The Elements of Friendly Software Design, 1982

You [the software developer] will need humility to recognize that the users are always the final and most appropriate judges of your work. Even though you’re the expert in interpreting your users’ comments and meeting their needs, their judgments of your work are final and without appeal.

– Nathaniel Borenstein, Programming As If People Mattered: Friendly Programs, Software Engineering, and Other Noble Delusions, 1991

Next: Automate Repetitive Tasks

2 Fundamental ↑

No. 9 – Decomposition

Large and complex things should be broken down into smaller, more manageable things. This can be done progressively, and recursively, at multiple levels.

It’s best if the number of things in each group is somewhere in the range of 3 - 15, with 7 being a sweet spot. The human brain seems fairly good at dealing with sets of this size.

This idea can be applied to system functionality, to software architectures, to work statements (where it results in a work breakdown structure), and to project staffing.

Decomposition is particularly powerful when done in conjunction with Cohesion and Loose Coupling.

One famous example of decomposition was performed by the Wright Brothers when they broke down the problem of human flight into three separate domains: lift, control and propulsion.

Another common example of decomposition in modern web applications is evident in the popular MVC pattern, in which application logic is subdivided into three separate areas: model, view and controller.

In Agile, it is common to have three levels of requirements decomposition, starting with epics, proceeding to features, and then to user stories.

Note, however, that detailed decomposition of requirements need not be done initially, and can often be profitably deferred until a feature is a high enough priority to be approaching scheduled implementation into code.

Words from Others on this Topic

The bulleted list of requirements is by far the most cost-effective and beneficial approach. It is simple to create; it is simple to read, regardless of background; and, when stored in a spreadsheet, database, or requirements management tool and augmented with annotations, it has incredible benefits to project management.

– Alan M. Davis, Just Enough Requirements Management: Where Software Development Meets Marketing, 2005

Next: Cohesion

4 People ↑

No. 27 – Developers Are Not Interchangeable

Aptitude, skills and experience all make a difference.

This is one reason why, as Fred Brooks pointed out long ago in the The Mythical Man-Month: Essays on Software Engineering, estimates for software development can be entirely misleading.

Software developers are all different, and different along many different dimensions. Here are some of the ways in which they differ:

Aptitude – Some developers are simply more capable than others. Productivity differences of an order of magnitude have been documented on multiple occasions.

General Experience – Some developers have had deeper and broader software development experiences than others. (This often correlates to years in the field, but not always: we sometimes find that developer A has had 20 years of experience, but developer B has had the same year of experience 20 times.) Successful experiences are also often much more helpful than the other kind, since developers will tend to repeat practices that they have used before, whether they were successful or not.

Particular Skills and Experience – Some developers may have background in a certain problem domain, or knowledge of a particular technology.

Verbal and Written Communications Skills – Some developers are good at communicating with customers, teammates and/or leaders, while others lack these skills. And some are good at communicating verbally, while others are better at communicating using the written word.

Productivity – Some developers seem to get things done, no matter what challenges they run into, while others seem to be easily sidetracked and tend to lose track of goals and commitments.

Teaming – Some developers play well with others, while some tend to operate more independently.

When considering these differences, it’s good to be familiar with the Dreyfus Model of Skill Acquisition, since experts often behave very differently than beginners when it comes to their tolerance/need for rigid rules. For more on this topic, see the Pagan Tuna post, “The Dreyfus Model of Skill Acquisition.” Also see “The Seven Stages of Expertise in Software Engineering,” by Meilir Page-Jones.

It’s also good to consider these differences when forming a team. You generally will want a good mix of skills and experience, and you will want teammates who can work well together.

And, of course, you need to maintain certain minimum requirements for your organization. You need people who are Smart and Gets Things Done, who enjoy learning, and who interact constructively with customers, management and teammates. I don’t mean to imply that these sorts of people are hard to find. Most of the people I’ve worked with in my career fit this description on a good day, and almost everyone I’ve known (myself included) fails to meet one or more of these standards on a bad day. And certainly all of us have room for development in these areas, and do indeed develop in positive ways over time.

On the other hand, there are situations where not everyone lives up to these standards consistently, where people are progressing slowly if at all, and where you can’t afford to wait for a long-term turnaround plan. These situations are unfortunate for all involved, but ignoring them doesn’t make them go away.

Talented people are the most important element in any software organization.

– Watts Humphrey, Managing the Software Process, 1998

Counterintuitively, employees already performing above average have the greatest room for growth. Great managers also know that it is hard work helping a talented person hone his talents. If a manager is preoccupied by the burden of transforming strugglers into survivors by helping them squeak above average, he will have little time left over for the truly difficult work of guiding the good towards the great.

– Marcus Buckingham and Curt Coffman, First, Break All the Rules: What the World’s Greatest Managers Do Differently, 1999

Next: Initiation

12.69.1 Managing Humans: Biting and Humorous Tales of a Software Engineering Manager ↑

Engineers and designers working together

Prior to Steve Jobs’ return to Apple, there was a decent centralized usability team equipped with those fancy rooms with one-way mirrors and video cameras. I’m certain these folks did significant work, but when Jobs returned, he shut it down and he cast the design teams to the wind. Each product team inherited part of the former usability team.

Now, I arrived after this reorganization occurred, so I don’t know the actual reasoning, but I do know I never saw those usability labs used once and I would argue that in the past decade Apple has created some of the most usable products out there. My opinion is that the choice to spread the usability design function across the engineering team was intended to send a clear message: engineer and designer need to party more… together.

I can’t imagine building a team responsible for consumer products where engineers and designers weren’t constantly meddling in each other’s business. Yes, they often argue from completely opposite sides of the brain. Yes, it is often a battle of art and science, but engineering and design want exactly the same thing. They want the intense satisfaction of knowing they successfully built something that matters.

– Michael Lopp, Managing Humans: Biting and Humorous Tales of a Software Engineering Manager, 2007

Next: Marsalis, Wynton and Ward, Geoffrey

8 Pagan Tuna Posts ↑

8.7 Lessons We (Should) Have Learned from the Web

Originally published at PaganTuna.com on 26 Jul 2015.

There are a number of basic principles that those of us in the Information Technology field should have learned from the tremendous success of the Internet and the World Wide Web.

Information of any enduring interest should be stored on the Web.

Every topic in which we have an interest should have its own unique address on the Web. The Internet calls this a Uniform Resource Locator (URL).

Each unique address should be permanent. The content at such an address can and should change over time, but the address at which we find that information should never change.

Information should be exchanged with others by passing the unique address back and forth – not by passing the information itself.

The unique address should be an intelligent identifier made up of words that identify the topic, rather than an arbitrary series of numbers and letters. It should be as concise as possible, but long enough to be meaningful. Another way to say this is that the unique address should be human-readable.

Revision or version identifiers should generally not be part of the unique address, unless the changes are so great that there is a need to identify a new and separate topic, and to preserve the location of the existing topic.

People who are knowledgeable about a topic should be able to update that topic’s information on the Web as easily and quickly as possible, with some way of preventing any lasting damage caused by mistakes.

Rather than duplicating existing information, we should freely refer to it via hyperlinks as needed. A hyperlink offers a gateway from one topic on the Web to another, related topic.

The information on a topic should be separated from its formatting. That is, people who are knowledgeable about a topic should be able to provide and update a topic’s information without worrying about things like fonts, colors and page layout.

All of the information on the Web should be accessible through a single application, known as a Web Browser.

For those of us actually working on the World Wide Web, none of this should come as a surprise. The Web is the engine of the Information Economy and, just as it was necessary to minimize mechanical friction in the Industrial Economy, it is essential to minimize communication friction in the Information Age. The principles above all serve to do exactly that: to make the latest and most accurate information on a topic available in as frictionless a manner as possible.

Examples of the success of these principles can be found everywhere you turn on the Web. Look at Wikipedia; look at Google; look at the URLs used by a company like Apple. Look at the success of Wikipedia. It uses every one of the principles stated above. And these principles have brought it success, not because someone thought they were cool, or because they were in political favor one year, but because they were found to work.

So why is it important to state these principles – now somewhat obvious to most of us – at this late date? Well, only because, even though these principles are now sacred canon on the Web, they are still violated with reckless abandon everywhere I look on corporate information networks.

Is this because these principles are unimportant inside the walled gardens of corporate intranets? No – minimizing communication friction is just as important there as it is on the open Web.

So why are these principles so often ignored? Well, because we have captive audiences inside corporations, and so we do not have the benefits of competition to teach us the importance of these principles through the hard lessons of failure.

One of the great lessons of evolution is that the best designs emerge through open competition – through the work of the blind watchmaker.

Those of us with eyes to see cannot always predict these things in advance, but we should be smart enough to identify and leverage them once they emerge.

See also:

Fighting Organizational Friction
Ten Reasons to Ditch Your Word Documents

Next: A New Model for Lean Culture

2 Fundamental ↑

No. 11 – Loose Coupling

When performing decomposition, it is best to group elements so as to minimize coupling between groups.

Coupling can be thought of as communication between groups, or knowledge of what’s going on within other groups, or dependencies of one group on another.

Note that loose coupling is desirable, whether the groups under consideration are teams of developers, or packages of data and methods.

Loose coupling tends to maximize the freedom of each group to handle its own work without consideration for what’s going on in other groups.

Encapsulation of data and internal components within objects is a notable feature of Object-Oriented Programming (OOP), and is one means by which tight coupling between objects may be avoided.

Loose coupling frequently offers a way to make internal improvements to one object or group without necessitating concomitant changes to other objects/groups that communicate with the first, thus minimizing the “ripple effects” of changes.

When decomposing the staff of developers needed on large projects, the idea of loose coupling results in the formation of relatively small, self-managed teams that contain all the resources they need to work relatively independently.

Postel’s Law can be thought of as another means of supporting loose coupling:

Be conservative in what you do; be liberal in what you accept from others.

This admonition, for both software interfaces and human ones, encourages us to stick to the straight and narrow in our own behavior, but be tolerant of minor quirks in others.

In other words, minimize the chances that minor changes, or small misbehaviors, from a second group will cause a failure of the first group.

Next: Communicate Clearly

12.73.1 The Toyota Product Development System: Integrating People, Process and Technology ↑

Managers should know what's going on

Unfortunately, many modern-day engineering managers believe their role in an organization is to attend meetings, keep abreast of the latest organizational policies, make the tough decisions about the big problems in the company, and generally look upward and outward. The philosophy seems to be that a good manager is good at delegating, and good engineers should work autonomously.

In the United States, ‘nosing around’ is being a busy body. It is a form of micromanagement. An effective manager should delegate and then stay out of the engineer’s way. For a Toyota manager, this is abdicating responsibility. How can you consult and advise if you do not know what is going on? If you have no more information about what is going on across the organization than any other engineer, then what is your value?

Next: A visceral lesson in what is important

2 Fundamental ↑

No. 15 – Show Rather than Tell

Language is a wonderful tool, but it is difficult for stakeholders to precisely parse large amounts of written text in order to provide reliable feedback on whether software developers are on the right track.

On the other hand, diagrams, screen layouts, and prototypes are often easier for people to understand and respond to.

This is not to say that words don’t have their place. But interactive dialogue about a visual representation is often much more productive than shipping written text back and forth for review and approval.

Frequent interactive demonstrations of working software still in development are particularly important as a means of showing your customers what you are up to. Customers are never more attentive and engaged than when they can see working software in action, and yet still have a chance to provide feedback that will either validate or help further refine the product.

Note that such demos require you to practice “iterative development,” possibly in addition to “incremental development.” Many authors and consultants blur the distinctions between these two different things, but Alistair Cockburn in particular makes the point in his piece “Using Both Incremental and Iterative Development” that they are different, even if they may both involve software development done in frequent, short sprints.

Incremental development means that the completed product is delivered in smaller increments, and is really the result of decomposing the overall product delivery into a number of smaller deliveries.

Iterative development, on the other hand, means that a partially completed feature is shown to the customer, with the intent of eliciting further feedback before finalizing the feature. As Cockburn points out, this is a means of planning some amount of time for some degree of rework.

Words from Others on this Topic

But in the end, for something this complicated, it’s really hard to design products by focus groups. A lot of times, people don’t know what they want until you show it to them.

– Steve Jobs, Business Week Interview with Steve Jobs, 1998

Next: Plan-Do-Check-Act

7 Caution ↑

No. 52 – Stay Focused on the Creation of Working Software for Real People

This was a major message of the Agile movement, which opened its Manifesto with the words: “We are uncovering better ways of developing software by doing it and helping others do it.”

To a great extent, this was a reaction to the Capability Maturity Model era, in which the actual act of software coding was often overshadowed by achievement of maturity levels, implementation of key process areas, documentation of processes, generation of artifacts and tallying of metrics.

As noted in the SEI paper, “CMMI or Agile: Why Not Embrace Both!”:

… if CMMI is used in the pursuit of maturity level numbers, the resulting process improvement efforts can sometimes lose sight of customer value, product, project value, and practical business goals.

The point here is that well-intentioned improvement efforts, whether initiated by management or by consultants, can all too easily prove a distraction to the actual production of working software to be used by real people, often to the detriment of everyone involved.

In particular, you would do well to avoid any sort of zealotry concerning any particular model being peddled by management consultants: while most such models can be useful, all are imperfect representations of reality, and most tend to take on a life of their own after a certain period of time. For more on this topic, see the Pagan Tuna post, “Model Mania.”

It would be wise to pay heed to the advice on this subject from

Steve Jobs: The Lost Interview

:

People get confused… companies get confused. When they start getting bigger they want to replicate their initial success. And a lot of them think, well somehow there’s some magic in the process of how that success was created. So they start to try to institutionalize process across the company. And before very long, people get very confused that the process is the content. That’s ultimately the downfall of IBM. IBM has the best process people in the world. They just forgot about the content. And that’s a little what happened at Apple too [which led to the Apple Lisa, a market failure in the 1980s]. We had a lot of people who were great at management process, they just didn’t have a clue as to the content. In my career, I’ve found that the best people are the ones that really understand the content – and they are a pain in the butt to manage, but you put up with it because they are so great at the content. That’s what makes good products: it’s not process, it’s content.

It’s ok to learn from the various software development gurus and movements you will find around you, but it’s best not to declare absolute allegiance to any of them. Remember that many consultants, speakers and authors are primarily interested in creating reliable revenue streams, and that their interests will not always coincide with yours. Also, I’ve worked with teams devoted to the CMMI as well as teams devoted to Agile and, in both cases, I’ve found mindless conformance to a set of precepts to be more harmful than any of the practices either of these movements was intended to correct.

Words from Others on this Topic

Wired: In your experience, what’s the best process for design?

Brooks: Great design does not come from great processes; it comes from great designers.

– Fred Brooks, “Master Planner: Fred Brooks Shows How to Design Anything”, 2010

He continues, “Remember, outcomes are what matter—not the process, not controls, or, for that matter, what work you complete.”

– Gene Kim and Kevin Behr and George Spafford, The Phoenix Project: A Novel About IT, DevOps, and Helping Your Business Win, 2013

Next: Pagan Tuna Posts

8 Pagan Tuna Posts ↑

8.3 The Core Design Principles for Teams

Originally published at PaganTuna.com on 09 Jul 2019.

I just came across a wonderfully scientific confirmation of the wisdom of agile software development teams.

The source was a surprising one: Evolutionary Biologist David Sloan Wilson’s book This View of Life: Completing the Darwinian Revolution.

The applicable knowledge comes in Chapter 8, “What All Groups Need.” Here’s the first paragraph that caught my attention:

Multilevel selection theory tells us that something similar to team-level selection took place in our species for thousands of generations, resulting in adaptations for teamwork that are baked into the genetic architecture of our minds. Absorbing this fact leads to the conclusion that small groups are a fundamental unit of human social organization. Individuals cannot be understood except in the context of small groups, and large-scale societies need to be seen as a kind of multicellular organism comprising small groups.

What this means is that, as human beings, we are hard-wired, not to compete and survive as individuals, but to work together cooperatively as members of small teams, with a maximum size of about 15 individuals: something that agile proponents have been preaching for close to two decades now.

But Wilson then gets much more specific, citing research done by Elinor Ostrom, the 2009 winner of the Nobel Prize in Economics, as well as a 2012 paper co-authored by Ostrom, Wilson and Cox, titled “Generalizing the core design principles for the efficacy of groups.”

Wilson lays out in his book, based on this published and recognized research, the eight core design principles (CDPs) that make the difference between success and failure of teams. I will paraphrase here.

Strong Group Identity with Clearly Defined Boundaries. This includes a shared understanding of the team’s goals, the boundaries of their resources, and the rights and obligations of being a team member.
Proportional Equivalence Between Benefits and Costs. Team members must be fairly rewarded based on their contributions.
Fair and Inclusive Decision-Making. Everyone gets a chance to participate in decision-making, and decisions are made in a way recognized by all to be fair. Also, decisions are made at the lowest possible level, both to confer a sense of empowerment, but also to allow decisions to be made based on local circumstances best known and appreciated by the team itself.
Monitoring Agreed-Upon Behaviors. The team must have a way of monitoring team members and detecting deviations from the team’s accepted norms.
Graduated Sanctions. This may start as friendly pressure from peers, but then may proceed to more serious consequences if the negative behavior persists.
Fast and Fair Conflict Resolution. When conflicts arise, teams must have a way to resolve them quickly and in a manner seen as fair.
Local Autonomy. Teams must have the freedom to conduct their own affairs, generally free of externally imposed rules.
Polycentric Governance. In large organizations that consist of multiple teams, relationships among teams must embody the same principles as the relationships among individuals within each team. This means that the core design principles above are scale-independent.

It’s interesting to note that Ostrom’s research was based on observations of the actual success and failure of many small teams, rather than on the invention of increasingly complex formulas and models often favored by traditional economists – certainly a vivid reminder of the way that Agile principles and methods came to be defined and accepted, often flying in the face of guidance offered by organizations such as the Software Engineering Institute and their Capability Maturity Models.

While Wilson’s teachings validate much of what Agile proponents have been preaching for some time now, they also provide a rigorous set of principles that can be used to evaluate any organization’s use of teams, as well as the operation of any particular team. This strikes me as valuable, because it can help free software developers from the sometimes insular guidance of one particular coach or manager, and potentially help resolve debates on these topics more quickly and authoritatively – an outcome right in line with CDP 6, as defined above.

I’ve excerpted some of Wilson’s work in this short piece in order to highlight material that should be of particular interest to software developers and their managers, but in doing so I certainly haven’t cherry-picked all the good stuff. I can enthusiastically recommend the entire book to everyone reading this, not just for its insights into the workings of teams, but perhaps even more importantly for insights into what it means to be human in the 21st century.

I’m always excited to find ideas and models that can be used across disciplines, and Wilson’s book amply delivers the goods in this department.

Next: Customer Communication